Guide to the William Warntz papers, [ca. 1955-1985]
Warntz, William papers, [ca. 1955-1985]
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
William Warntz papers, [ca. 1955-1985]
4392
William Warntz, 1922-.
54 cubic ft.
Correspondence, teaching materials, notes, reports, professional papers, source materials, manuscripts.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, teaching and administrative materials and studies in the field of geography by William Warntz, professor of geography and regional planning.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Geographer.
William Warntz received a B.S., A.M., and Ph.D. in Economics from the University of Pennsylvania. He taught at the University of Pennsylvania and was a research associate in the Department of Astro-Physical Sciences at Princeton University and for the American Geographical Society. He served as Professor of Theoretical Geography and Regional Planning in the Graduate School of Design, Harvard University. In 1971, he was appointed Professor of Geography and Departmental Chairman at the University of Western Ontario. He died in 1988.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers include general correspondence, student papers; correspondence and reports from his work at Harvard; administrative correspondence, teaching materials; and student notes from the University of Western Ontario; miscellaneous personal and professional papers; and notes, source materials, computer printouts, and manuscripts on subjects including macrogeography and income, Newton and Varenius, the diffusion of universities and printing in Europe, place names, cartography, and other topics in geography.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Warntz, William, 1922-.; Harvard University. Graduate School of Design.; University of Pennsylvania.; University of Western Ontario. Dept. of Geography.
Subjects:
Geography.; Mathematical geography.; Geography--Study and teaching.; Income--United States.; Regional science.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Part of Regional Science Archive.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. General Correspondence
  - mid-1960's-1980's (Box 1)
    J.Q. Stewart
    Miscellaneous correspondence
    World War II navigation records and correspondence
  - mostly 1980's (Box 2)
    Wide variety of topics
    Clare Hall, Cambridge
  - 1985-1988 (Box 3)
    Mostly period at the University of Cambridge
  - 1970's-1980's (Box 4)
  - Correspondence from Bill Bunge, 1980's (Box 54)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 18)
- Series II. Early Career: Harvard
  - Research analyses on a variety of topics (Box 5)
    American Geographical Society, Pennsylvania and Harvard periods
  - Correspondence and reports, 1950's-1960's (Box 6)
    American Geographical Society
    Princeton
    Harvard
  - Correspondence, research reports and proposals, Harvard period (Box 7-9)
  - Harvard series on theoretical geography (Box 10)
    Originals, documentation
  - Research: Harvard computer graphics (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, Harvard period (Box 11)
    Distances in the Man-Made Environment-Penguin correspondence
- Series III. Western Ontario
  - Administrative correspondence as Chairman of Geography Department, University of Western Ontario, 1970's (Box 12)
  - Correspondence and reports as Chairman of Geography department, University of Western Ontario (Box 13-14)
  - Teaching materials, University of Western Ontario (Box 15-16)
    Outlines, exams, examples of student reports
    Notes and student projects, University of Western Ontario
- Series IV. Miscellaneous Personal and Professional Items
  - Annual calendars (diaries of events, schedules) (Box 17)
  - Book order/purchase receipts (Box 17)
  - Research expense records (Box 17)
  - Research proposals (Box 18)
  - Research expenses (Box 18)
  - CVs and geographical details (Box 18)
  - Job applications (Box 52)
  - Warntz's papers as a student (Box 19)
  - Audio and data tapes (Box 20)
  - Films and slides (Box 20)
- Series V. Projects
  - Newton and Varenius
    - Source material (photocopies) (Box 21)
      - Newton
      - Varenius
    - Supporting source material (photocopies) (Box 22-23)
      - Newton
      - Varenius
    - Research on Geographia Generalis by Varenius (Box 24-25)
      - Sir Isaac Newton
      - Vermeer's painting of The Geographer
      - Original translations by Warntz from Latin/German
      - Analysis
      - Grant proposals
    - Photocopies of Latin, German and English editions of Varenius and Newton: source materials for Warntz's research (Box 26-27)
  - Diffusion of Universities
    - Source materials (photocopies) for research on European printing, universities and population potentials, 1500-1800 (Box 28-29)
    - Diffusion of universities and printing in Europe 1500-1800 (Box 30-31)
      - Population potentials (Box 30)
      - Original analysis/data (Box 30-31)
  - Macrogeography
    - Macrogeography (Box 32-33)
      - Population/income potential research, 1972
      - United States
    - Macrogeography and income U.S.A. (computer output) (Box 34-35)
      - Completed 1960's, Harvard
  - Place Names
    - Place names: research data and analysis (Box 36)
    - Place names: research, analysis (Box 37)
  - United States Universities
    - Research analysis (Box 38-39)
      - U.S. universities
      - Who's Who
      - Potential patterns
      - Macro patterns of U.S. university football
    - Values research of university students (Box 40-41)
      - Survey forms
      - Computer output
      - Analyses
    - United States migration research tabulations, graphics, computer printout (Box 42)
    - Research analyses (Box 43-44)
      - U.S. educational establishment/ Who's Who
      - Universities, 1970's-1980's
  - Geography, the Innocent Science
    - Geography, the Innocent Science (Box 45)
      - Manuscripts
      - Experiments
      - Correspondence with William Bunge
  - Map Projection
    - Map projection projects (Box 46)
      - Historical mapping
      - Q problem on sphere
      - Shape of earth
    - Research analysis (Box 47-48)
      - Contour mapping
      - Properties of surfaces
      - Networks
      - Pressure patterns
      - Continentality
    - Global patterns (Box 49-50)
      - Global patterns of populations potential
      - Global patterns of temperature/pressure (computer output)
  - United States Space Economy
    - United States space economy (Box 51)
      - Intensification
      - Potentials
      - Income fronts (data, graphics, manuscripts)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Original unpublished materials (Box 19, 52)
      - Distances in the man-made environment (Box 52)
      - Translation/commentaries of 19th- and early-20th-century books/papers, from Polish, German and French (Box 52)
      - Correspondence with publishers (Box 52)
      - Research on Canadian universities and the Canadian space economy (Box 52)
      - Computer research on tall buildings (Box 52)
    - Surface properties research, computer graphics, etc. (Box 20, 53)
    - Research: U.S. college/football (Box 53)
    - Geography of and for College Students (Box 53)
    - Correspondence and drafts (Box 53)
      - Geography Now and Then
      - Geographers and What They Do
      - Place Names, Probabilities, Priorities
    - Television series, Philadelphia (Box 54)
      - Materials/correspondence, 1963-1964
      - Boston, 1966-1967
    - Drafts: Breakthroughs in Geography (Box 54)
    - Reprints of publications (Box 19)
    - Warntz TV show on geography (Box 20)
    - Various/translations by Warntz (Box 54)
- Series VI. Maps and Oversized Materials
  - Original research maps
    Population potential
    Map projections
    Pressure patterns
  - Original finished cartographics for Warntz publications